JavaNCSS - Credits

Copyright Notice

JavaNCSS is free software distributed under the GNU Lesser General Public License. Copyright Chr. Clemens Lee.

Credits

Authors

The currently active crew with permission to write into the source code repository can be found here [2009-02-07].

Thanks to Metamata and Suntest for the JavaCC parser generator and especially the Java grammar on which JavaNCSS is based.
Ted Leung for a patch for the -out option.
Steve Jernigan for an Ant task fro JavaNCSS. This task can be downloaded separately from http://sourceforge.net/projects/javancss2ant/ but is distributed with JavaNCSS as well. This task has also some additional features such as checks of user defined thresholds on individual metrics.
Pääkö for a patch for the -recursive feature [2002-03-16].
John Wilson for a patch to use "\r\n" on Windows to end lines for JavaNCSS's ascii output.
Emilio Gongora and Guillermo Rodriguez for patches to count number of lines of comments. Applying these patches is not finished yet and the only result you can see already is the the new Javadocs info for packages.
Phillip Wells for working on Steve Jernigan's Ant task and submitting it to the Ant project to be added into the optional.jar file [2002-06-08].
Ross Gardler (ross at saafe.org) donated an XSLT stylesheet to convert the xml output of JavaNCSS to a format very close to HTML. This can be used to generate custom HTML pages for your project [2002-06-15].
Terry Skelton (tskelton15 at attbi.com) donated an XSLT stylesheet to convert the XML output of JavaNCSS to HTML. [2002-07-05].
Yves Coene (Yves.Coene at spacebel.be) donated XSLT stylesheets which generate beautiful SVG charts from the JavaNCSS XML output [2002-09-04].
Rajesh Raheja (Rajesh.Raheja at oracle.com) donated an XSLT stylesheet, which generates a simple HTML report of all metrics which exceed a certain limit [2003-05-11].
Chris Povirk for a patch in the XML handling for enums [2006-06-12].
David Chwalisz for enhancements to the ant build.xml script [2006-10-06].
Simon Brandhof for opening and moving JavaNCSS to the Codhaus development infrastructure (and Jira for bug tracking) [2009-02-07]. This will open up development to better collaboration with other developers and possibly will lead to new talent contributing much needed updates.
Hervé Boutemy for moving the whole project to Maven and cleaning up all kind of code areas (encoding etc.) [2009-02-07].
Freddy Mallet for a draft version of a new Java parser, which will allow easier extension of JavaNCSS by traversing Java source code via the visitor pattern [2009-02-07]. Hopefully this might also lead to more people being able to fix grammar bugs or updating the grammar to Java language extensions.
Sébastien Reynaud for many difficult Java grammar fixes [2009-06-01].
Peter Kofler for many Java grammar fixes [2014-07-12].

Thanks To

Frans van Gool for HtmlViewer (which got replaced by JavaHelp since JavaNCSS version 7).
Thanks to the users of JavaNCSS and to the people who provided valuable feedback and requests.
Thanks to Glen Cordrey for the tip how to set the JAVANCSS_HOME variable automaticly in javancss.bat.
Joseph Kiniry for bug reports for the parser and example test code (2001-06-16).
Jonathan Doughty for the error report of JavaNCSS not being able to handle JDK 1.4 assertions.
Carsten Lergenmüller for two error reports regarding the '-recursive' feature.
Chris Williamson for finding a rare parsing bug having to do with inner, outer, and super classes [2002-05-11].
Ted Leung for writing an Ant task for JavaNCSS of his own. Unfortunately I never got around looking into it and adding it to JavaNCSS. Finally when I found the time I decided to go for Steve Jernigan's task, as that adds some new features to JavaNCSS and has detailed documentation. Thought Ted's task has a simpler interface with its parameter names sticking nearer to the original JavaNCSS options [2002-06-08].
David Brandt fixed the wrong Javadocs per Function value for XML output [2002-07-21].
Vesa Karvonen for feedback regarding the overloaded 'functions' element in the XML DTD, which has led to the conversion stylesheet 'javancss_no_functions_overloading.xsl' [2002-08-04].
Again Vesa Karvonen for a bug report that revealed the incorrect production of XML output in conjunction with some exotic locale setting [2002-09-03].
Brad Kiewel for patching the build.xml Ant file to add a manifest to the javancss.jar file, so JavaNCSS can now be executed via java's -jar option [2002-09-04].
Anthony Sobey for pointing out that the '&&', '||', and '?' statements haven't been considered for measuring cyclomatic complexity numbers [2003-12-14].
Bill Burcham for adding SVG doctype definitions to the SVG stylesheets [2003-12-22].
Wally Bowles for the suggestion to use 'Method' instead of 'Function'. Has been applied so far only to an optional HTML output style sheet [2004-08-08].
Don Morrison, Lakshman Srilakshmanan, Eduardo Sherington for various bug reports [2006-05-14].
Tom Mitchell for bug reports and test code in the Java 1.5 parser code [2006-06-12].
Charles L, Anver Sotnikov, James Burton, Byron du Preez, Martin Lehofer, Darren M. Siegel, David Chwalisz for a bug reports and test code in the Java 1.5 parser code [2006-10-06].
Don Kautz and Isabelle Guimiot for bug reports and test code for the Java 1.5 parser code [2008-04-08].
Jean-Laurent de Morlhon for good morale when moving to Codehaus [2009-02-07]!

JavaNCSS - A Source Measurement Suite for Java

Ever wondered how many lines of code or how many classes there are in  the Sun JDK? Curious about the size of your own projects - or do you want to keep track of your work-progress. That's what JavaNCSS is for.

JavaNCSS is a simple command line utility which measures two standard source code metrics for the Java programming language. The metrics are collected globally, for each class and/or for each function.

Here is an example about what JavaNCSS prints out for the Sun JDK 1.1.5 java.* source tree (update: JDK 1.5 api source tree consists of 569'830 ncss).

JavaNCSS can optionally present its output with a little graphical user interface. To interactively select Java source files for counting, Jacob (a Java class browser and project manager) can be used for this purpose.

JavaNCSS can also be used out of an Ant build.xml script as it comes bundled with an Ant task written by Steve Jernigan. The JavaNCSS Ant Task is documented on a separate page.

You can always find the newest version of this page at: http://javancss.codehaus.org/ (was previously at http://www.kclee.de/clemens/java/javancss/).

Table of Contents

Features and Metrics' JavaNCSS Provides
System Requirements
Downloading
Usage

XSLT Stylesheets

Specification
Development
Release History
Copyright Notice
Credits
Related Links

Features and Metrics JavaNCSS Provides

Metrics can be applied to global-, class-, or function-level.
Non Commenting Source Statements (NCSS).
Cyclomatic Complexity Number (McCabe metric).
Packages, classes, functions and inner classes are counted.
Number of formal Javadoc comments per class and method.
Average values are calculated.
Command line driven.
A GUI is provided for better output browsing as well as the integration of JavaNCSS in a project manager and class browser named Jacob for easy selection of input source files.
XML output (optional).
XSLT stylesheets provided for further generation of HTML, and SVG reports and as a basis for your own custom reports.
Ant task (written by Steve Jernigan).
Support for Java 1.5 syntax (generics, enums, etc.).
100% Pure Java.
Free software (GNU GPL).

System Requirements

Java JDK >= 1.4.1

Downloading

JavaNCSS Version 33.54

Downloading Java Development Kit

JavaNCSS requires the Java Developer's Kit (JDK) Version 1.4 or above. Since you already seem to have Java source code you want to measure, I assume you already have a JDK :). If not, you can download it via web from Javasoft. Follow the link to "JDK 1.4" and download the version applicable to your environment.

Usage

Make sure javancss-30.51/lib/javancss.jar, javancss-30.51/lib/ccl.jar, and javancss30.51/lib/jhbasic.jar are added to your CLASSPATH.

Then to start JavaNCSS type: java javancss.Main. As an alternative you can edit and use either the JAVANCSS.BAT or javancss file. Just change the JAVA_HOME and CLASSPATH variables according to your system. Make sure you did include the swingall.jar archive in the classpath.

Now for the first run type in (beeing in the javancss-30.51 directory itself):

./bin/javancss -gui test/*.java

or

./bin/javancss -gui -recursive test

For regression test of JavaNCSS use:

java javancss.test.JavancssTest

If no parameter is provided for JavaNCSS, standard input (stdin) is used as the input stream. Multiple java source files can be specified in the command line. If a '@' char is put in front of a file name, then not this file will be measured but its content will be interpreted as a list of Java source files that shall be counted. The '@' functionality can be used recursively inside this file as well. Wild cards are not supported yet. (If the operating system processes the command line for the program, then you are lucky. Windows doesn't do that.) Instead use something like cat *.java | javancss or type *.java | javancss. Of course, this can lead to ambiguities when mixing source files that belong to a package with files that doesn't.

If no option is given, JavaNCSS only calculates the total non commenting source statements (NCSS) of the given input.

JavaNCSS can also be used conveniently via Ant. For details have a look at the JavaNCSS Ant Task page, especially at the example at the bottom of that page. You can also have a look at the build.xml file that gets distributed with JavaNCSS itself (see "javancss" target).

Synopsis

javancss [-option] stdin | [@]source_file*

Options

-ncss
This is the default which counts total non commenting source statements and nothing else.
-package
Collects the metrics data for each package. This is the most top level view javancss offers for your projects. Take a look here what javancss prints out for the Sun JDK 1.1.5 java.* source tree.
-object
Collects the metrics data for each class/interface. For an example program output, look here.
-function
Collects the metrics data for each function. For an example program output, look here.
-all
The same as '-package -object -function'.
-gui
Opens a gui to presents the '-all' output in tabbed panels.
-xml
Output in xml and not in ascii format. Additional option '-all' is recommended.
-out file
Output goes normally to standard output, with this option an output file can be specified.
-recursive
Java file in sub directories will be parsed as well. Be careful not to get caught in an endless loops because some Unix links.
-check
Trigger JavaNCSS self test suite.
-version
Prints out the version of JavaNCSS.
-help
Prints out some basic information.

XSLT Stylesheets

JavaNCSS comes with some XSLT stylesheet (javancss-30.51/xslt/javancss2text.xsl and javancss-30.51/xslt/javancss2html.xsl). These stylesheets can be used to convert XML output from JavaNCSS to ASCII or HTML output. In case of the ASCII output this is of course quite boring and much slower as JavaNCSS creates the identical output by default anyway. But you can use this stylesheet (or any of the others shipped as well) as a starting point to have your own presentation format. You could also change sort rules (e.g. sort by NCSS) or add your own filters to the output (e.g. show only methods with NCSS greater some limit).

Assuming you have e.g. Xalan2 installed and somewhere in your path is a shell script named 'xslt' that knows how to invoke Java with the Xalan 2 main processor class (org.apache.xalan.xslt.Process), here is how you can make use of JavaNCSS' XSLT stylesheet:

cd javancss-30.51
javancss -all -xml -recursive src > example.xml
xslt -in example.xml -xsl xslt/javancss2text.xsl

Have fun. If you create a useful new stylesheet for JavaNCSS, I would be happy to get a copy of it.

SVG Output

Yves Coene <Yves.Coene@spacebel.be> has donated some XSLT stylesheets which produce beautiful SVG charts out of JavaNCSS's XML output.

Use e.g. batik as an SVG viewer and have a look at the example files in directory xslt/svg under the JavaNCSS home directory.

Here is an example SVG chart file.

Generation of SVG files is similar to using other XSLT stylesheets as described above.

Specification

Non Commenting Source Statements (NCSS)

Statements for JavaNCSS are not statements as specified in the Java Language Specification but include all kinds of declarations too.
Roughly spoken, NCSS is approximately equivalent to counting ';' and '{' characters in Java source files.

Actually, the NCSS counter gets incremented by one for each:

| Examples | Comment
Package declaration | package java.lang; |
Import declaration | import java.awt.*; |
Class declaration | - public class Foo {
- public class Foo extends Bla { |
Interface declaration | public interface Able { |
Field declaration | - int a;
- int a, b, c = 5, d = 6; | No matter how many fields get actually declared through a comma separated list, and no matter if these fields get actually initialized, only one statement is counted. So "int a, b, c = 5, d = 6;" gets only +1 count, not four or even six (let me know if there is good reason to count it differently).
Method declaration | - public void cry();
- public void gib() throws DeadException { |
Constructor declaration | public Foo() { |
Constructor invocation | - this();
- super(); |
Statement | - i = 0;
- if (ok)
- if (exit) {
- if (3 == 4);
- if (4 == 4) { ; }
- } else { | expression, if, else, while, do, for, switch, break, continue, return, throw, synchronized, catch, finally
Label | fine : | normal, case, default

Not counted are empty statements, empty blocks or semicolons after closing brackets. Of course, comments don't get counted too. Closing brackets also never get counted, the same applies to blocks in general.

In some cases consecutive semicolons are illegal according to the JLS but JavaNCSS still tolerates them (thought JavaNCSS is still more strict as 'javac'). Nevertheless they are never counted as two statements.

Cyclomatic Complexity Number (CCN)

CCN is also know as McCabe Metric. There exists a much hyped theory behind it based on graph theory, but it all comes down to simply counting 'if', 'for', 'while' statements etc. in a method. Whenever the control flow of a method splits, the "CCN counter" gets incremented by one.

Each method has a minimum value of 1 per default. For each of the following Java keywords/statements this value gets incremented by one:

if
for
while
case
catch
&&
||
?

Note that else, default, and finally don't increment the CCN value any further. On the other hand, a simple method with a switch statement and a huge block of case statements can have a surprisingly high CCN value (still it has the same value when converting a switch block to an equivalent sequence of if statements).

Copyright Notice

JavaNCSS is free software distributed under the GNU General Public License. Copyright Chr. Clemens Lee.

Credits

Authors

The currently active crew with permission to write into the source code repository can be found here [2009-02-07].

Thanks to Metamata and Suntest for the JavaCC parser generator and especially the Java grammar on which JavaNCSS is based.
Ted Leung for a patch for the -out option.
Steve Jernigan for an Ant task fro JavaNCSS. This task can be downloaded separately from http://sourceforge.net/projects/javancss2ant/ but is distributed with JavaNCSS as well. This task has also some additional features such as checks of user defined thresholds on individual metrics.
Pääkö for a patch for the -recursive feature [2002-03-16].
John Wilson for a patch to use "\r\n" on Windows to end lines for JavaNCSS's ascii output.
Emilio Gongora and Guillermo Rodriguez for patches to count number of lines of comments. Applying these patches is not finished yet and the only result you can see already is the the new Javadocs info for packages.
Phillip Wells for working on Steve Jernigan's Ant task and submitting it to the Ant project to be added into the optional.jar file [2002-06-08].
Ross Gardler (ross at saafe.org) donated an XSLT stylesheet to convert the xml output of JavaNCSS to a format very close to HTML. This can be used to generate custom HTML pages for your project [2002-06-15].
Terry Skelton (tskelton15 at attbi.com) donated an XSLT stylesheet to convert the XML output of JavaNCSS to HTML. [2002-07-05].
Yves Coene (Yves.Coene at spacebel.be) donated XSLT stylesheets which generate beautiful SVG charts from the JavaNCSS XML output [2002-09-04].
Rajesh Raheja (Rajesh.Raheja at oracle.com) donated an XSLT stylesheet, which generates a simple HTML report of all metrics which exceed a certain limit [2003-05-11].
Chris Povirk for a patch in the XML handling for enums [2006-06-12].
David Chwalisz for enhancements to the ant build.xml script [2006-10-06].
Simon Brandhof for opening and moving JavaNCSS to the Codhaus development infrastructure (and Jira for bug tracking) [2009-02-07]. This will open up development to better collaboration with other developers and possibly will lead to new talent contributing much needed updates.
Hervé Boutemy for moving the whole project to Maven and cleaning up all kind of code areas (encoding etc.) [2009-02-07].
Freddy Mallet for a draft version of a new Java parser, which will allow easier extension of JavaNCSS by traversing Java source code via the visitor pattern [2009-02-07]. Hopefully this might also lead to more people being able to fix grammar bugs or updating the grammar to Java language extensions.
Sébastien Reynaud for many difficult Java grammar fixes [2009-06-01].

Thanks To

Frans van Gool for HtmlViewer (which got replaced by JavaHelp since JavaNCSS version 7).
Thanks to the users of JavaNCSS and to the people who provided valuable feedback and requests.
Thanks to Glen Cordrey for the tip how to set the JAVANCSS_HOME variable automaticly in javancss.bat.
Joseph Kiniry for bug reports for the parser and example test code (2001-06-16).
Jonathan Doughty for the error report of JavaNCSS not being able to handle JDK 1.4 assertions.
Carsten Lergenmüller for two error reports regarding the '-recursive' feature.
Chris Williamson for finding a rare parsing bug having to do with inner, outer, and super classes [2002-05-11].
Ted Leung for writing an Ant task for JavaNCSS of his own. Unfortunately I never got around looking into it and adding it to JavaNCSS. Finally when I found the time I decided to go for Steve Jernigan's task, as that adds some new features to JavaNCSS and has detailed documentation. Thought Ted's task has a simpler interface with its parameter names sticking nearer to the original JavaNCSS options [2002-06-08].
David Brandt fixed the wrong Javadocs per Function value for XML output [2002-07-21].
Vesa Karvonen for feedback regarding the overloaded 'functions' element in the XML DTD, which has led to the conversion stylesheet 'javancss_no_functions_overloading.xsl' [2002-08-04].
Again Vesa Karvonen for a bug report that revealed the incorrect production of XML output in conjunction with some exotic locale setting [2002-09-03].
Brad Kiewel for patching the build.xml Ant file to add a manifest to the javancss.jar file, so JavaNCSS can now be executed via java's -jar option [2002-09-04].
Anthony Sobey for pointing out that the '&&', '||', and '?' statements haven't been considered for measuring cyclomatic complexity numbers [2003-12-14].
Bill Burcham for adding SVG doctype definitions to the SVG stylesheets [2003-12-22].
Wally Bowles for the suggestion to use 'Method' instead of 'Function'. Has been applied so far only to an optional HTML output style sheet [2004-08-08].
Don Morrison, Lakshman Srilakshmanan, Eduardo Sherington for various bug reports [2006-05-14].
Tom Mitchell for bug reports and test code in the Java 1.5 parser code [2006-06-12].
Charles L, Anver Sotnikov, James Burton, Byron du Preez, Martin Lehofer, Darren M. Siegel, David Chwalisz for a bug reports and test code in the Java 1.5 parser code [2006-10-06].
Don Kautz and Isabelle Guimiot for bug reports and test code for the Java 1.5 parser code [2008-04-08].
Jean-Laurent de Morlhon for good morale when moving to Codehaus [2009-02-07]!

Related Links

Clemens' Java Page - Other Java stuff I did.
Sonar is an open source code quality management platform. Sonar enables to collect, analyze and report metrics on source code. Sonar not only offers consolidated reporting on and across projects throughout time, but it becomes the central place to manage code quality. With no complex infrastructure, Sonar fulfills needs in terms of code quality, whether it is to make an audit or implement a continuous improvement process.
Jacob - A development tool that embeds the Emacs editor. It can also be used as a gui-frontend for JavaNCSS.
Clemens' PSP Page - JavaNCSS can be used as a tool for the Personal Software Process (PSP).
JavaCC - A Java compiler compiler from SunTest. JavaNCSS is done with it.
JDepend - Mike Clark's JDepend "traverses a set of Java source file directories and generates design quality metrics for each Java package. JDepend allows you to automatically measure the quality of a design in terms of its extensibility, reusability, and maintainability to effectively manage and control package dependencies."

While JavaNCSS simply lets you know how much source code you have to deal with (ncss metric), JDepend informs you about the package structure of your code and helps you spotting weaknesses in your global code organization, e.g. identifying dependency cycles, creating a few independent packages on which most other package rely on, etc.

You can use JDepend as a quantitative measurement tool as well.

ProGuard - ProGuard is a class file shrinker and obfuscator by Eric Lafortune. It differs from other offerings in its simple and compact configuration, its speed, and its modest memory usage.

ProGuard is an application which has made use of JavaNCSS in an unexpected way: "... I've taken the liberty of using JavaNCSS for producing test results with ProGuard, and, vice versa, for producing statistics about ProGuard. You can find the references in the Results section and the Quality section respectively. The latter section shows how I have integrated JavaNCSS in a nightly build process."

SLOCCount is a set of tools for counting physical Source Lines of Code (SLOC) in a large number of languages of a potentially large set of programs. This suite of tools was used in a Estimating Linux's Size to measure the SLOC of an entire Linux distribution. It runs on Linux, Windows, and hopefully on other systems too. To run on Windows, you have to install Cygwin first.
Cetus Links: Object-Orientation / Metrics